<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model
  href="https://vault.tei-c.org/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"
  schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
  type="application/xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
   <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Contributions to the Theory of Pictorial Form.</title>
                <author>P. Klee</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt> 
                <publisher>Istituto Italiano di Studi Germanici</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Rome</pubPlace>
                <date>2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <respStmt><resp>Translated by</resp><name></name></respStmt>
                    <respStmt><resp>Scientific responsability of</resp><name>Tiziana Mancinelli</name></respStmt>
                    <respStmt><resp>Coordinated by</resp><name>Eleonora De Longis</name></respStmt>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="div_Klee_introduction">
                <pb/>
                <head type="main">A. Winter semester lectures 1921-1922 <date>Nov. 14, 1921</date></head>
                    <p>
                       By way of introduction, a brief clarifi-
                       cation of concepts. First, what the concept 
                       of "analysis" encompasses: In ordinary con-
                       versation one usually hears mention of 
                       chemists' analyses. For instance, a certain 
                       preparation sells well due to its excellent 
                       effect. The manufacturer's profits make 
                       other manufacturers curious, and they 
                       take a sample of it to the chemist so 
                       that he can analyze it. He must proceed 
                       methodically in order to break the prepa-
                       ration down into its component parts. To 
                       solve the riddle.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                       In another case, a stimulant proves to have 
                       grave consequences for health. Here also the 
                       chemist must be called upon to reveal the 
                       harmful components through an analysis.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                       In both cases the given substance is a 
                       whole composed of different, initially unknown
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                       parts; the components are what is sought after.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                       In our business, the motives or 
                       inducements that lead us to make analyses 
                       are of course different. We do not analyze 
                       works that we would like to copy, nor works 
                       we have reason to distrust.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                       We investigate the paths that 
                       another has followed in the creation of 
                       a work in order, by becoming familiar 
                       with these paths, to get going ourselves.
                       This type of examination should prevent 
                       us from regarding the work as something 
                       rigid, immutably fixed. By means of such 
                       exercises we can prevent ourselves from 
                       sneaking up on a finished work only to 
                       quickly pluck up what stands out the 
                       most and run off with it.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                       A special type of analysis is the
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                       examination of the work through the stages 
                       of its emergence. I designate this type with 
                       the word "genesis." The first book of Moses, 
                       which deals with the creation of the world, 
                       is also called Genesis. There it is written 
                       what God created on the first day, what 
                       on the second, and so forth. The universe 
                       surrounding us undergoes a historical 
                       articulation.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                       We are makers, working practitioners, 
                       and hence it is natural that here we shall 
                       move chiefly in a formal domain, all the 
                       while not forgetting that before the formal 
                       beginning, or (put more simply) before the 
                       first stroke, lies an entire prehistory: not 
                       only, say, the yearning, the human desire 
                       to express oneself, not only the outward 
                       necessity to do so, but also a general human 
                       condition, whose orientation is called a 
                       weltanschauung, which, with an inner necessity,
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                       urges its manifestation in this or that 
                       direction.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                       I emphasize this lest the misunder-
                       standing arise that a work consists only 
                       of form.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                       But on the other hand, I must empha-
                       size here even more that the most precise 
                       scientific knowledge of nature, plants, 
                       animals, the earth and its history, or 
                       of the stars is useless to us if we are 
                       not provided with all the tools for their 
                       representation; that the profoundest 
                       understanding of the synergy of these 
                       things in the universe is of no use to 
                       us if we are not also equipped with forms 
                       directed towards that purpose; that the 
                       deepest feeling, the most beautiful soul, 
                       is useless unless we have the proper forms 
                       at hand.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                       <s part="I"> Here it means renouncing the excep-
                       tional fluke that on occasion earns the 
                       dilettante honor with a successful work that</s>
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                       After these general premises, I shall 
                       begin where the pictorial form actually 
                       begins, with the point that sets itself 
                       in motion.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <s part="F">can, as an isolated case, shame the professionals.</s>
                    </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div_Klee_lesson1">
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        After the <graphic url=".../number1"/> pen or something else 
                        with a pointed tip is applied, a line 
                        promptly emerges. (The more freely it takes 
                        its jaunt initially, the clearer its mobile 
                        nature will be.)<graphic url="..."/>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        But if I apply a line with the angular 
                        edge of some black or colored material, then 
                        a plane emerges (initially, and if the jaunt 
                        it takes is very restricted).
                        <graphic url="..."/>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        If we had a material with which to push planes 
                        forth with a similar effect, then we could 
                        inscribe such a notional sculpture in space.
                        <graphic url="..."/>
                        But that is, alas, a utopia.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        So let us tarry for the moment with the most 
                        primitive device: with the line. In the pre-
                        history of peoples, where writing and drawing 
                        still coincide, it is the given element. Also our
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        children usually begin in this way. One day 
                        they discover the phenomenon of the mobile 
                        point, and one can scarcely imagine their 
                        enthusiasm. With the greatest of freedom, 
                        the pen initially moves wherever it pleases. 
                        Once these first works are examined, 
                        however, the discovery is immediately made 
                        that the paths traversed have now become 
                        fixed in ink. Now then, children who 
                        continue to take pleasure in chaos are of 
                        course not image-makers, but other children 
                        will soon progress to a certain order. 
                        The critique of the journeys made by the 
                        pen begins. The chaos of the initial play 
                        gives way to an incipient conformity to set 
                        principles and patterns.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        The freedom with which the line is 
                        guided submits to the anticipated final 
                        effect. Now, out of caution, one begins 
                        to work with very few lines to achieve an 
                        effect. One remains primitive.
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        Yet one cannot persist stubbornly in this 
                        primitivity. One will have to discover a 
                        means of enriching the meager end result 
                        without destroying or blurring the simple, 
                        clear arrangement. One must classify.
                    </p>
                    <p>Linear active</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson1_fig1"/>
                        <figDesc> free line ab : fig. 1</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson1_fig2"/>
                        <figDesc>
                            free line ab
                            accompanying line a1-b1: figs. 2, 3, 4
                        </figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson1_fig3"/>
                        <figDesc>ditto</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson1_fig4"/>
                    </figure>
                <pb/> 
                    <figure>
                        <figDesc>free line with detours: figs. 5 and 6</figDesc>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson1_fig5"/>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson1_fig5a"/>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson1_fig6"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <figDesc>
                            Fig. 7: two secondary lines, the principal line 
                            imaginary
                        </figDesc>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson1_fig7"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <figDesc>Fig. 8: the same</figDesc>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson1_fig8"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <figDesc>Fig. 9: similar</figDesc>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson1_fig9"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        With all these examples, the principal line goes 
                        forth freely and unbound. It is, so to speak, a 
                        stroll taken for its own sake. Without a goal.
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p> This new line, however,</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson1_fig10"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        has a deadline, it wants to go as fast as 
                        possible to 1, then to 2, to 3, and so 
                        on. One might say it is rather more like 
                        running errands than taking a stroll. The 
                        straight lines indicate as much. But both 
                        the free line and the line with a time 
                        limit are of a purely active type.
                    </p>
                    <p>Linear medial</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson1_fig11"/>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson1_fig12"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        In these new cases the time-constrained 
                        line circumscribes the figures of planes 
                        like a triangle or a square.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Or, here, <graphic url="..."/>a circle and <graphic url="..."/>an ellipse.
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        As a line it is marked by its calming 
                        character and by its lack of a beginning or 
                        an end. Considered in elemental terms (as an 
                        action of the hand) it is certainly still 
                        a line, but once it has been completed, 
                        the mental image of linearity is superseded 
                        immediately by that of planarity. With it, 
                        the mobile character also disappears (no one 
                        looking at the disk of the moon would attempt 
                        to ride a carousel around its perifery), 
                        replaced by the notion of the most complete 
                        quiescence (chiefly in the instance of the 
                        circle).
                    </p>
                    <p>Linear passive</p>
                    <p>
                        The lines in this case have an entirely passive 
                        character.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson1_fig15"/>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson1_fig16"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        One indeed also sees lines, but it is not 
                        a matter of linear actions but of the linear 
                        results of planar actions. The line is not 
                        made but rather is suffered.
                    </p>
                <pb/> <!--come inserire il testo in verticale, a margine?-->
                    <p>
                        Running contrary to the trajectory of this 
                        short account of the line, and at the same 
                        time contained within it, is an account of 
                        the plane. When active, the line divided  
                        [it] into imaginary planes. In between, the 
                        plane-character pushed its way forth; it then 
                        became active when the line was designated as 
                        passive.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        The plane, when purebred, is the element 
                        at rest. But if it starts to move,
                        <graphic url="..."/>
                        then it approaches the line-character.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        The further
                        <graphic url="..."/>
                        the line AB moves forth,
                        the thinner the described plane becomes in 
                        relation to its length, until finally one may 
                        speak of the coincidence of A and B, with which 
                        we have arrived once again at the active line.
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>Nov. 21, 1921</p>
                    <p> Exercise: The Violin. Models: one cello, two violins.</p>
                    <p>
                        Opening words: the violin as a perfect form, as a work 
                        of art, as an independent personality (not a machine). 
                        The view, for example, of Picasso, Braque, and the 
                        current Parisians.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Analytical beginnings proposed for those who are 
                        unsure; afterward, a freer compositional control with 
                        the present forms. Tacit wish: the freest compositions, 
                        more about the violin qua violin.
                    </p>
                    <p>Results, for the time being, of a more analytical nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div_Klee_lesson2">
                <pb/> 
                    <p><graphic url=".../number2"/>Nov. 28, 1921</p>
                    <p>
                        We were occupied 14 days ago with, among other 
                        things, the free line. I chose as an example a type 
                        that corresponded to a relaxing walk, without an 
                        express purpose, without an express goal.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        This line had a certain inherent quiescence 
                        and harmony, and as a theme in a composition its 
                        realization would have required accompanying forms 
                        and so would have corresponded more to the folk-
                        song form in music than to a more artistic form.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Sure enough, only accompanying forms or substitute  
                        forms joined the inherently quiescent line,
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson2_fig1"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        accompanying forms, in part (fig. 1), of absolutely converging 
                        character; or (fig. 2) of effectively converging character;
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson2_fig3"/>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson2_fig2"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        or (3) of effectively converging nature while maintaining the 
                        independence of the accompanying line, rather like the path
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>of a person with his or her dog running about freely.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson2_fig4"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        The essential difference between this new 
                        construct and the previous examples of 
                        convergence is best illustrated if we think 
                        of each line, for instance, as the path taken 
                        by a person. You can speak of friendship in 
                        the previous examples; there is no drifting 
                        apart. But with this new divergent example 
                        we see our fellow stroller crossing our path 
                        just once, at point D.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/><graphic url=".../lesson2_fig5"/>
                        <cb n="right"/>
                        Let us imagine this (fig. 5) to 
                        be railway tracks. Now, is there 
                        not something very misleading 
                        about this? Because these lines 
                        are truly divergent enough! 
                        Railway tracks that are 
                        constantly spreading further 
                        apart would result in the 
                        loveliest derailment. Or, 
                        if you took the opposite 
                        direction:
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/><graphic url=".../lesson2_fig6"/>
                        <cb n="right"/>
                        railway tracks that will soon 
                        intersect at some point beyond; 
                        is this not almost more alarming?
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        How does this happen, then? Well, without noticing, 
                        we have stepped out of the concept of planarity 
                        into the territory of space, into the third 
                        dimension. We are doing perspective.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Last time, we established with regret, first 
                        of all, that we have no kind of spatial writing: 
                        Unlike the movement from points <graphic url="..."/> to lines
                        or the movement from lines <graphic url="..."/> to planes, we cannot
                        analogously move
                        <graphic url="..."/> planes forth with any visible effect, so 
                        as to produce solids. We must therefore make do 
                        with perspective.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        But it will not take long to explain nor 
                        prove difficult if we confine ourselves to its 
                        principal features. And the explication of the 
                        inherent phenomena is quite remarkable!
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/><graphic url=".../lesson2_fig7"/>
                        <cb n="right"/>
                        These (fig. 7), then, are railway 
                        tracks. Railway tracks lie on 
                        crossties. How do I depict this? 
                        If I had drawn tracks on the 
                        plane, like a surveyor or carto- 
                        grapher, then we would have the 
                        image of two parallel lines,
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        and the ties would be placed at regular 
                        distances.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson2_fig8"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        Represented spatially, however, this graphic 
                        image looks fundamentally different. The distance 
                        between the ties increases noticeably, as most 
                        Europeans know, towards the foreground.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson2_fig8a"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/><graphic url=".../lesson2_fig9"/>
                        <cb n="right"/>
                        The front of the locomotive 
                        stands at a right angle to 
                        the plane lying between 
                        the tracks. (We 
                        have thus right 
                        at the outset 
                        projected the 
                        greatest spatial 
                        height.)
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        Now, in this new third dimension we can imagine 
                        more new angles and planes (so the new plane 
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/><graphic url=".../lesson2_fig10"/><graphic url=".../lesson2_fig11"/>
                        <cb n="right"/>
                        in fig. 11 
                        stands at a 
                        right angle 
                        to the plane 
                        in fig. [10]),
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/><graphic url=".../lesson2_fig12"/>
                        <cb n="right"/>
                        and we arrive finally at the 
                        construction of a space into 
                        which we can walk standing 
                        upright.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/><graphic url=".../lesson2_fig13"/>
                        <cb n="right"/>
                        Once again we begin 
                        by imagining the 
                        rails but limit 
                        ourselves to one 
                        tie lying far 
                        in the distance 
                        and another tie 
                        lying very near: 
                        that is, only two 
                        ties. We divide 
                        both ties into 
                        the same number 
                        of equal parts; here, for example, in three places.
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/><graphic url=".../lesson2_fig14"/>
                        <cb n="right"/>
                        In this manner we can go from  
                        crosswise graduation to grad-
                        uation lengthwise and see 
                        before us in perspective the 
                        plane of a floor depicted 
                        with five parallel lines.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Which line stands out in particular?... 
                        Naturally, the middle one (from 2 to 2)
                    </p>
                    <p>And in what capacity? As the vertical.</p>
                    <p>
                        What does this vertical indicate? That at 
                        the point where it stands we ourselves have 
                        also stood.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson2_fig15"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        If we take a step to the left, then the 
                        vertical shifts to point 1, and the plane of the 
                        floor takes this shape 
                        in the projection.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson2_fig16"/>
                    </figure>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        While with a vantage point at no. 3, the result 
                        is this new image of  
                        the projection. 
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson2_fig17"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        When I travese such a plane,<graphic url="..."/> the vertical remains 
                        vertical, as long as I don't leave the line, and the 
                        other lines radiate towards me.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson2_fig18"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        But if I leave the line, then the image deflects 
                        towards the opposite side  
                        in either case.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson2_fig19"/>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson2_fig20"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        (And now, incidentally, we have made our acquain- 
                        tance with the phenomenon of counter-motion!!)
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/> Now we want
                        <cb n="center"/><graphic url=".../lesson2_fig21"/>
                        <cb n="right"/>
                        to stand still again 
                        and so proceed as 
                        before with cross
                        wise graduation. 
                        And the result is 
                        this image
                        (fig. 21).
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Again a space that we can walk into. I ask you to 
                        pay particular attention as well to the side walls. 
                        Just as on the plane of the floor the vertical 
                        assumed special importance, here the horizontal does.
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/><graphic url=".../lesson2_fig22"/>
                        <cb n="right"/>
                        What does this 
                        horizontal mean? 
                        (Now, the answer 
                        is almost ripe.)
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson2_fig23"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        Inside the now familiar space I have constructed 
                        a second one that offers the eye a view of its upper 
                        plane. Hence, one can speak more aptly of a volume 
                        than of a spatiality that ends within our eye's visual 
                        field, since actual spaces extend beyond our visual 
                        field. (We are inside them.) Thus, a volume that 
                        offers the eye a view of its upper plane.
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson2_fig24"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        In this case the volume does not offer a  
                        top view of its upper plane. If we assume it  
                        is made of glass, then it offers, on the contrary,  
                        a view of this plane from below.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Such a horizontal plane that can be seen  
                        from below, however, is situated above our eye; <graphic url="..."/> 
                        it is higher than we are.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        The other horizontal plane our eye sees from 
                        above is lower than our eye; it lies below us.<graphic url="..."/>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/><graphic url=".../lesson2_fig25"/>
                        <cb n="right"/>
                        In this third case, 
                        however, something 
                        special occurs. The  
                        eye is unable to re- 
                        cognize the upper plane 
                        as such, whether from  
                        above or from below;  
                        rather, it appears
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/>
                        as a horizontal 
                        line.
                        <cb n="center"/><graphic url="..."/>
                        <cb n="right"/>
                        The volume is thus 
                        exactly as high as 
                        our eye.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        (Splitting hairs, one could add that the lengthwise 
                        and crosswise graduation coincide.)
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        What is valid for this horizontal plane 
                        is logically valid also for the corresponding 
                        horizontal lines on both side walls. These 
                        horizontal lines at eye level appear again as 
                        horizontal in the perspectival projection.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/><graphic url=".../lesson2_fig22"/>
                        <cb n="right"/>
                        So the answer is 
                        there. It is: "eye 
                        level."
                    </p>
                <pb/>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson2_fig26"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        The person, or the bearer of the gaze, may now stand 
                        in front, at A, or further back (like at B, C, D); 
                        from each of these vantage points the phenomenon of 
                        the horizontal occurs. One can conceive a large plane 
                        extending through all these points, A1 to D1 (a plane 
                        that, as demonstrated above, one can never see): 
                        the plane of the horizon. Remaining at point A1, for 
                        example, a huge circular disc.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson2_fig27"/>
                    </figure>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        This horizon-disc separates the entire visible 
                        space into an upper and a lower part, as if we 
                        found ourselves in a large round can that divides 
                        into can and lid.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="..."/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        This sign corresponds to the edifice of the 
                        human being, taking into account the earth's 
                        attraction. The feeling for the vertical is alive 
                        in us so that we do not fall, and if we must, we 
                        correctively stretch out our arms so as to again 
                        balance out the error. In exceptional cases we 
                        extend the horizontal, like the tight-rope walker 
                        with his balancing pole.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Note: The questions already raised pertaining to perspec
                        tive and everything else that seems worth knowing can all 
                        be verified or investigated by means of a very simple 
                        apparatus. A pane of glass is brought into a fixed vertical 
                        position and placed near the eyes in front of the object 
                        to be projected. The observations must be made with one 
                        eye, fixed in its position. With ink or grease pencil the 
                        important essential lines of the object are drawn onto the 
                        pane of glass. <graphic url="..."/>
                        Lines recorded on a pane of glass that is not standing 
                        vertically will be seen as incorrect, distorted images. 
                        Similar distorted images are produced by photographers who, 
                        from a low angle, take pictures of an object that can be 
                        easily controlled in <graphic url="..."/>
                        perspective, for <graphic url="..."/>
                        example, a house.
                        To be precise, such images are not
                        at all false objectively. 
                        (or logically)
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        are closer to the eye than the upper windows and there- 
                        fore are wider. But that is where a human being objects, 
                        because one wants to have the horizontal and the vertical 
                        fixed so that one does not begin to wobble, to get 
                        dizzy. The value of this whole procedure lies simply in 
                        the possibility of controlling, of monitoring. Drawing 
                        in correct perspective has therefore no value, because 
                        everyone can do it in this way.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Further examples yet: Van Gogh's perspective 
                        instrument; Hodler's "carré"
                    </p>
                    <p>December 5 (Exercises)</p>
                    <p>
                        Representations of equilibrium, drawn and shaded 
                        according to equilibrium constructions on the plane.
                    </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div_Klee_lesson3">
                <pb/> 
                    <p><graphic url=".../number3"/>December 12, 1921</p>
                    <p>
                        We were left standing with the tight-rope walker 
                        and his balancing pole, as the extreme realiza-
                        tion of the symbol of the equilibrium of forces.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig1"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        We had derived this symbol from the rudiments 
                        of perspective theory, as the distinctive sign 
                        for the meaning of vertical and horizontal. The 
                        extension of the (seen) horizontal line onto the 
                        horizontal plane or, in short, onto the horizon, 
                        brought us the spatial  <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig2"/>
                        extension of this symbol:
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Today I would like to make the weighing of  
                        forces on either side the object of our 
                        investigation, namely, those forces that result 
                        from the earth's force of attraction, in other 
                        words, the weighing-up of weights. Forces of this 
                        kind are closest to us, since we ourselves are  
                        physically subject to these same laws of weight. 
                        For this, we still want to assume the solid 
                        ground on which we usually stand,  and not 
                        (as happens exceptionally) go into the water or 
                        indeed the air.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        As an instrument for this weighing, a pair of 
                        scales can be as useful to us as it is to the 
                        grocer in his shop.
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig3"/>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig3a"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        A set of scales looks roughly like this. It 
                        weighs two weights against each other and, 
                        as there are only two, they can operate in 
                        a plane. For, wherever they are located in 
                        space, I can always bring two points into one 
                        single plane. (Supposing)
                    </p>
                    <p>Fully spatial scales would look like this:</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig5"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        In this case, a set of spatial scales that 
                        extends over three axes, AB, CD, and EF. With 
                        these scales one can ascertain the weights on 
                        the walls of a space constructed as a hexagon 
                        (fig. 6).
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        *Supposing the one plane has been correctly weighed, 
                        then we can bring the scales into a new position and 
                        against the first plane weigh a second one opposite.*
                        (a fully... etc.)
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig6"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        With this now no longer entirely simple little 
                        machine, it would be unwise to make our first 
                        experiments, and you will agree with me that we 
                        are justified in limiting ourselves to the plane.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        It is the same whether the set of planar scales 
                        is standing or hanging (figs. 3 and 3a); what is 
                        essential is the cross made by the horizontal with 
                        the vertical. This is the spirit of the scales,
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>and we can leave out the pans without detriment.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig7"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>If we disturb the scales on one side by overloading,</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig8"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>then the image changes in this way:</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig9"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p> If we correct it with a counter-load,</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig10"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p> then it looks like this:</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig11"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p> What is new is this cross:</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig12"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        Now, I remind you of the complementary relationship 
                        of lines to planes, as I presented it the time 
                        before last. The planes on which this kind of play 
                        of forces occurs are usually bounded, for example,
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/>
                        a quadri-
                        lateral
                        like this:
                        <cb n="right"/><graphic url=".../lesson3_fig13"/>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/>
                        and with the new
                        cross, like this:
                        <cb n="right"/><graphic url=".../lesson3_fig13a"/>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Bearing in mind that complementary relationship, 
                        this figure (13a) permits two conceptions, one 
                        linear and one planar. Conceived in terms of lines, 
                        it is a quadrilateral with both diagonals; in terms 
                        of planes, it is a quadrilateral divided into four  
                        triangles. These four triangles arrange themselves, 
                        particularly if we do not take the quadrilateral 
                        as a square, as two pairs of triangles lying 
                        opposite each other.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig14"/>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig15"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        It is characteristic of their position that they 
                        thrust against each other with their tips and, in 
                        fact, with the force of impact directed vertically 
                        and horizontally.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <cb n="left"/><graphic url=".../lesson3_fig16"/>
                        <cb n="center"/><graphic url=".../lesson3_fig17"/>
                        <figDesc>
                            The scales are here 
                            again. (fig. 18) 
                        </figDesc>
                        <cb n="right"/><graphic url=".../lesson3_fig18"/>
                    </figure>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        The primitive simplicity of this case of a 
                        balancing act has allowed me to proceed 
                        symbolically, so to speak. The result is of a 
                        symmetrical nature, because the same kind of 
                        weights are on both sides.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        A state of equilibrium diverging from 
                        symmetry could be illustrated with the image 
                        of a pair of scales with, for example, two one-
                        pound weights in one pan and, in the other, one 
                        750-gram weight and one 250-gram weight.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig19"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        But we will now have to leave the matter 
                        there. We must operate with pictorial elements 
                        by means of which the feeling of weight can be 
                        discussed.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        First of all, some cases in which we certainly 
                        cannot speak of equilibrium.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig20"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        20) Difference in extension, accumulation of energy 
                        on the right side through addition.
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig21"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        21) Difference in tone value, additional load of black 
                        energy on the right
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig22"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        22) Difference in chromatic tone value, additional 
                        load of color energy on the right 
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig23"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        23) Difference in color value, additional load on 
                        the left because of the color character.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Let us proceed to the corrections. For fig. 
                        20, we reach into our element box, into the line 
                        compartment, and place what is missing on the left.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig20a"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        For figure 21, we reach into the black tone compart- 
                        ment and add a small black square next to the light 
                        gray square.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig21a"/>
                    </figure>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        For figure 22 we reach into the red tone 
                        compartment and proceed accordingly.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig22a"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        For figure 23 we reach into the pure color 
                        compartment and load the blue side, which is 
                        too light, with some yellow, perhaps?
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig23a"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        It is certain that with the correctly 
                        measured dose on either side, we can consider 
                        equilibrium to be established, that is, an 
                        equilibrium that is no longer identical with 
                        symmetry. In order, however, for either side 
                        to be identified with certainty as part and 
                        counterpart, so to speak, surely something 
                        beyond this rather rough comparison is needed. 
                        A local imperative must intervene, one which 
                        cannot be avoided in our assessment. Every 
                        conclusive example goes fundamentally beyond a 
                        loose comparison:
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig24"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        Here such a local imperative has intervened, i.e., 
                        a particular idea underlies the position of the 
                        energic weights:
                        Example of configuration
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        The axis AB, overloaded with the heavier 
                        red, has sunk to A and risen to B. Originally 
                        it lay horizontally (a-b). Both these axes, the 
                        original ab and the new AB share a single point 
                        in common, the point C. C is therefore the 
                        pivot. The result of this rotation of the axis 
                        is that red, on the left, is lower than light 
                        red, on the right. Now to compensate, dark red 
                        intervenes and will be in a position to provide 
                        the compensation.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        A little drama of horizontals, construed 
                        anthropomorphically: I began to totter towards 
                        the left and reached out towards the right with 
                        my hand, trying to find a hold somewhere so as 
                        not to fall.
                    </p>
                    <p>Or, by transferring the action onto the vertical:</p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/><graphic url="..."/>
                        <cb n="right"/>
                        The upper part of the 
                        body is too heavy; the 
                        vertical falls to the 
                        left if the correction 
                        below does not occur in 
                        time. One widens the 
                        base by stretching out 
                        the left leg.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        The character of both these schematic 
                        compositions is centric, i.e., their arrangement 
                        is in reference to a center point.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Thinking now of such compositional actions 
                        repeated many times from below to above, we 
                        then have a series of such center points, one 
                        above the other, and we can then no longer 
                        speak of a centric arrangement. This series of 
                        points C takes on the appearance of a spinal 
                        column, as you will see.
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/><graphic url=".../lesson3_fig26"/>
                        <cb n="right"/>
                        I is thought of as a 
                        socle, II as the first 
                        stone on this socle, 
                        laid just at the tipping 
                        point. One can imagine 
                        the force that would 
                        tip it over having 
                        its expression in the 
                        arrow, →, and its measure in the weight, w.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        If one now thinks of this sort of construction 
                        carried forward, alternating from left to right, 
                        then an actual tipping will be avoided. Each stone 
                        pulls, so to speak, at the vertical axis, each 
                        wants to make the horizontal pivot at its point CI 
                        or CII or CIII.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        By unraveling the basic schema of this building 
                        method, we obtain the following constructs (in 
                        addition to other possibilities):
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig27"/>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig28"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        Buildings of this kind (like towers) are comparable 
                        to a person standing. As the effort to maintain his or 
                        her balance becomes taxing, the person sits down and 
                        reduces this task by about half. If he or she leans back 
                        against something, then only a remnant of the balancing
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        activity is left, but nevertheless still a 
                        remnant, because someone who has fainted might 
                        fall off a chair in certain circumstances. 
                        This remnant only disappears completely in 
                        the recumbent position. The person becomes a 
                        building block.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Compositions of a recumbent character have, in  
                        comparison to the vertebral construction (figs. 27 
                        and 28), a certain becalmed quality.
                    </p>
                    <p>The base widens, and with it so does the</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig29"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        horizontal, at the cost of the vertical. An 
                        appreciable reduction of tension occurs--an epic 
                        tempo in comparison to the drama of the vertical 
                        character--which naturally does not exclude a 
                        weighing-up on each side. The vertical is always 
                        still there!
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig30"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        The weighing-up only stops when the diagonal ceases, 
                        when the scales freeze in place, e.g., with this 
                        most primitive rhythm of the structural, where there 
                        are only horizontal or only vertical lines:
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig31"/>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig31a"/>
                    </figure>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        I am arriving at the essence of the weight of 
                        pictorial elements. If I ask,
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig32"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        "Do you consider this square heavy or light?" As 
                        such, there is no definite answer. For if the 
                        answer were "light!" and I added a second much 
                        smaller square,
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig33"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        it would thus immediately invalidate the hasty reply, 
                        for now the square makes an impression of being 
                        considerably heavier. One can now say that the 
                        large square is heavy in comparison with the small 
                        one and that the small one is light in comparison 
                        with the large one. Relativities.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson3_fig34"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        Now, however, both these weights can hold their own 
                        against one another. And why? One is lighter in terms 
                        of energy, though much larger, and the other is very 
                        heavy in terms of energy, though small in size.
                    </p>
                <pb/>
                    <p>
                        One cannot decide so lightly which is actually 
                        heavier. In this undecided case, the assumption 
                        of the given equilibrium is intuitively close 
                        at hand, implied in our indecisiveness.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        The effect of weight is more a question of 
                        quantity on the left, in comparison to the 
                        right, where it expresses itself more qualita- 
                        tively. Relativities!
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        The assumption that black is heavier than 
                        white only applies as long as we move on the 
                        white plane as a precondition. In this case, 
                        if we disregard color, black is the device for 
                        developing energy. The blacker the energy, the 
                        heavier the impression of weight compared to 
                        the white plane. Again, a relativity.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        If, by contrast, one takes a black plane 
                        as given, then a black energy cannot therefore 
                        express itself on that plane, precisely because 
                        its weightiest development, deep black, would 
                        not stand out at all. Therefore in this case, 
                        as long as we disregard color, white is the 
                        given energy, and it is precisely the brightest 
                        white that has the qualifications for producing 
                        the heaviest effects.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        On a gray plane of medium tone, black and 
                        white can rival each other as energies.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Outdoors, for example in the countryside, 
                        one may assume a white plane as given if the 
                        weather is foggy. The things that are closest 
                        by (and thus the heaviest) stand out to us  
                        as particularly dark, whereas heading into  
                        the distance everything grows gradually
                    </p>
                <pb/>
                    <p>
                        lighter until finally it merges entirely with 
                        the background.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        In the dark of night, areas of brightness, 
                        such as illuminated windows, have the strongest 
                        and heaviest effect.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        And on a normal day, one can observe the 
                        interaction of dark and light against a medium 
                        tonality.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        In physics one speaks of specific weight 
                        in comparison to water. In our case, there 
                        are several specific weights, in comparison to 
                        white, to black, or to the average of the two 
                        (and to every gradation between).
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        After that, the world of colors introduces 
                        yet more relationships: colors on a red 
                        background... colors on a violet background... 
                        etc.
                    </p>
                    <p> January 9, 1922</p>
                    <p>
                        Exercise in initial capital letters (Antiqua).
                        a) intrinsically balanced letters, like H, A, M, etc.
                        b) letters lacking equilibrium, like P, F, etc. 
                        The composition to be arranged in solemn stasis.
                    </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div_Klee_lesson4">
                <pb/> 
                    <p><graphic url=".../number4"/>January 16, 1922</p>
                    <p>
                        Last time, the opposition between compositional 
                        and structural characters became evident.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <graphic url="..."/> Structural rhythms of 
                        the lowest degree of development appeared, 
                        which find their numerical expression in the 
                        aggregation of simple units: 
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig1"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>and</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig2"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        Addition of simple units in a linear 
                        direction.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Crossing both directions produces this new 
                        structural image,
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/><graphic url=".../lesson4_fig3"/>
                        <cb n="right"/>
                        which can be described 
                        as the addition of 
                        units in the direction 
                        of two dimensions. This 
                        image, though extending 
                        through its two dimen- 
                        sions, still remains
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        at the lowest position in the order of structural 
                        characters.
                    </p>
                    <p>A step higher, there is this new structure:</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig4"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>or this structure:</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig5"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        (figs. 4 and 5) If one compares their 
                        numerical expression, both structures resemble 
                        each other to a tee. The difference lies only 
                        in the choice of means for representing them 
                        pictorially. (fig. 4) The first case makes 
                        use only of the measures "single segment" and 
                        "double segment," while the second case makes 
                        use only of the weights, light and dark. In 
                        other words, measure in one case, weight in the 
                        other.N Or, in one case, a force that achieves 
                        the greater output, 2, without a greater effort 
                        but through a doubling of the time in which it 
                        occurs; and in the other, a force that works 
                        towards its greater output only with doubled 
                        energy.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Note: I would like to provide a picture frame with a 
                        hook; I measure the upper horizontal very accurately to 
                        find the center. I attach the hook exactly at the midpoint
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        and am convinced that now nothing else is lacking. Yet 
                        in the end, the picture still hangs crooked on the wall.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        And why is it hanging crooked? Because the 
                        density of the wood is not uniform or because the glass 
                        is possibly thicker and heavier on one side. In short, I 
                        have made the mistake of measuring instead of weighing.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        In another case I want to cut a very long wooden 
                        pole into exactly two halves. It seems to me that the 
                        simplest way is to balance the pole on a sharp edge. I 
                        am pleased with my sharp-wittedness and happily saw on. 
                        The result: two pieces of entirely different lengths. Why,  
                        then? The wood must have varied in its thickness and 
                        weight, and I made the mistake of proceeding by weighing 
                        instead of measuring.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        So, on the one hand, measure; on the other, 
                        weight. I return to both our higher-order structures 
                        and consider the numerical series they share in 
                        common:
                        1 + 2 + 1 + 2 + 1 + 2 + 1 + 2, etc.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        This series does not change if I represent it thus: 
                        (1 + 2)+(1 + 2)+(1 + 2)+(1 + 2), etc.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        This, then, equals:
                        3   +   3   +   3   +   3    And this is the 
                        regular repetition of a type of unit (tripartite), 
                        and therefore again a purely structural case.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        This algebraic maneuver corresponds pictorially 
                        to the following conception:
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig4a"/>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig5a"/>
                    </figure>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        thus  3 + 3 + 3 + 3 + 3 = I + I + I + I + I, where 
                        Roman numeral one stands for a higher unit.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig6"/>
                        <figDesc>
                            If we extend fig. 5 into two dimensions,
                            then the vertical 
                            sum of the squares 
                            lying on top of 
                            each other =
                            11+10+11+10+11+10, etc.
                            =(11+10)+(11+10)+(11+10), etc.
                            =21+21+21, etc.
                            =I+I+I, etc.
                            Vertical
                            sum:  
                            11 + 10 + 11 + 10 + 11 + 10, etc.
                        </figDesc>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig6a"/>
                        <figDesc>
                            the horizontal 
                            sums present the 
                            same scenario;
                            thus, I+I+I, etc. 
                            in the horizontal 
                            direction.
                        </figDesc>
                    </figure>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        Thus, the entire square of this structure is 
                        articulated as joined pairs of two neighboring 
                        squares in the horizontal and vertical:
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig7"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        Whereupon there emerges an articulation into four
                        sided, four-part units with a value of six:
                        6 + 6 + 6       I + I + I
                        +   +   +
                        6 + 6 + 6   or  I + I + I
                        +   +   +
                        6 + 6 + 6       I + I + I
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        This regular repetition of a higher unit is, 
                        however, characteristic of a structural formation. 
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig7a"/>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig8"/>
                    </figure>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        (figs. 7a and 8) A variant of the concept of 
                        this chessboard structure with emphasis on the 
                        diagonals offers us a linear structure with two 
                        different qualities of line, which again can be 
                        read reciprocally as the rhythm of four-part units. 
                        These units take the shape of squares standing on 
                        their vertices.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        And in this way one can invent fascinating 
                        higher-order structural motifs; as soon as any 
                        repeating rhythm can be verified, its structural 
                        character is established.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        It cannot be claimed that such rhythms are 
                        inherently of an organic character. This is 
                        confirmed at a first glance at the corresponding 
                        numerical series. Every organism is an individuum, 
                        a word meaning "indivisible." That is to say, one 
                        cannot remove anything from it without altering the 
                        character of the whole or, in the case of living 
                        beings, without impairing the function of the whole 
                        or even stopping it outright. Likewise, nor can one 
                        add something to it.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Our numerical series and numerical complexes 
                        retain their sub-organic, dividual character 
                        if we, instead of 1 + 1 + 1 + 1,   put: 1 + 1 + 1,
                        or: 1 + 1 + 1 + 1 + 1 + 1;
                        instead of 3 + 3 + 3 + 3,   put: 3 + 3 + 3,
                        or: 3 + 3 + 3 + 3 + 3;
                        instead of 6 + 6 + 6  put: 6 + 6  or: 6 + 6 + 6 + 6
                                   +   +   +       +   +      +   +   +   +
                                   6 + 6 + 6       6 + 6      6 + 6 + 6 + 6
                                   +   +   +                  +   +   +   +
                                   6 + 6 + 6                  6 + 6 + 6 + 6
                                   +   +   +                  +   +   +   +
                                   6 + 6 + 6                  6 + 6 + 6 + 6
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        One might be reminded, from Natural History, 
                        of primitive organisms made of few cells or 
                        of those single-cell bacteria that are only 
                        noticeable in great masses.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        A great advantage, however, also lies in the 
                        individual insignificance of the structural 
                        rhythms: they can be easily arranged into 
                        an organic, individual whole, supporting the 
                        organism's being--without opposing it anywhere. 
                        *Note*
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Individual rhythms, conversely, cannot be 
                        reduced to one or to similar numbers but must 
                        stop inexorably at proportions like 2:3:5 or 
                        7:11:13:17.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Note *  They are therefore suitable for livening up deficient 
                        places in certain compositions; they have long been 
                        familiar as wallpaper patterns, and they are suitable 
                        for livening up the surfaces of books and portfolios 
                        in a neutral manner.
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        I now cross over to the domain of music. Here the 
                        bar is the fundamental structure. For the ear, the bar  
                        is to a certain extent latent, but it is nevertheless 
                        experienced throughout as a structural web on which 
                        the quantities and qualities of the musical ideas 
                        play out.
                    </p>
                    <p> The standard meters are duple and triple.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig9"/>
                        <figDesc>
                            (fig. 9)    
                            duple meter or   
                            two-beat bar
                        </figDesc>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig10"/>
                        <figDesc>
                            (fig. 10)   
                            triple meter or 
                            three-beat bar
                        </figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig11"/>
                        <figDesc>
                            (fig. 11) Variant of the duple 
                            meter, a two-beat bar with 
                            bipartite substructure,  
                            or four beats
                        </figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig12"/>
                        <figDesc>
                            (fig. 12) Variant of the duple 
                            meter, with tripartite 
                            substructure, or six beats  
                            (bipartite)
                        </figDesc>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig13"/>
                        <figDesc>
                            (fig. 13) Variant of the triple 
                            meter, with tripartite sub
                            structure, or nine beats
                        </figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig14"/>
                        <figDesc>
                            (fig. 14)  Variant of the four-beat bar, with a tripartite 
                            substructure of the quarters, or twelve beats
                        </figDesc>
                    </figure>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        The rare, off-kilter bars of five or seven beats 
                        are unequally wieghted two-beat bars:
                        2 + 3  
                        or  
                        3 + 4  
                        or  
                        3 + 2  (five)
                        4 + 3  (seven)
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        This representation of bar structure corresponds 
                        to the quantitative conceptualization; it is the 
                        translation of the absolute measures of time into the 
                        absolute measures of length (mensural-rhythmic).
                        Inherent to it is the shortcoming that, with just the 
                        length measures themselves, we cannot conclusively 
                        assign fixed values to the bar units (indicated by 
                        the bar lines).
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Where? <graphic url="..."/> Where is the bar
                        line?
                        What is indicated by special signs like |? ×? |? •? ?
                        They indicate that at the points where they are 
                        situated, different accentuations occur.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        This shows us the path to another type of 
                        representation that will do better justice, from a 
                        sensorial point of view, to the essence of the bar 
                        structures. This representation would illustrate 
                        the quality of the parts of the bar especially 
                        clearly. It would be the representation of the 
                        relationships among weights, the qualitative 
                        treatment of the bar structures (weight-rhythmic)
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig15"/>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig16"/>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig17"/>
                    </figure>
                <pb/>
                    <p>
                        By observing a conductor, we can obtain more 
                        planar images of bars. A quick look at the baton 
                        can reveal them to us.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        In a four-beat bar the conductor beats the first 
                        value downward, 
                        <graphic url="..."/> the second up and to the left, <graphic url="..."/> the third
                        from left to right, <graphic url="..."/> and the fourth from the
                        right <graphic url="..."/> upwards to the starting point of the 
                        first value.
                    </p>
                    <p> This overall image emerges:<graphic url="..."/></p>
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/>
                        Considering
                        the dynamic
                        element,
                        <cb n="center"/><graphic url=".../lesson4_fig18"/>
                        <cb n="right"/>
                        which coincides closely 
                        with the particular qualities 
                        of verticals and horizontals
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/>or:
                        <cb n="center"/><graphic url=".../lesson4_fig19"/>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        The image of the triple-beat bar is similarly engaging.
                        <cb n="left"/><graphic url=".../lesson4_fig20"/>
                        <cb n="center"/><graphic url=".../lesson4_fig20a"/>
                        <cb n="right"/><graphic url=".../lesson4_fig20b"/>
                    </p>
                <pb/>
                    <p>
                        On such a foundation I can now attempt to represent 
                        pictorially a thematic musical construct, in one or more 
                        voices.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        I choose two bars from a work in three voices by Bach
                        and examine them microscopically according to the follow- 
                        ing schema: 
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson4_fig21"/>
                        <figDesc>
                            Since music without dynamics sounds mechanical and expression- 
                            less, I choose the qualitative representation, C, and give 
                            the line more or less weight, analogous to the quality of 
                            the tone, while the quantitative representation is expressed 
                            in B in the vertical strokes for bars and parts of bars. 
                            Note: fig. 22 follows in the form of an insert.
                        </figDesc>
                    </figure>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        With this example (insert, fig. 22), which attempts 
                        to represent, pictorially and objectively, a thing 
                        that is simultaneously abstract and absolutely real, 
                        we can learn quite a few things: first of all, the 
                        possibility of this new representation in itself.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        : Furthermore, we can identify the relationship 
                        among the two or three "voices," which pertains to 
                        their place according to length and height;
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        : Their relationship among each other, which 
                        pertains to their degree of individualization. 
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        One moment it is two voices, the next it is 
                        three that sound together (and occasionally a single 
                        voice could even sound alone).
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Both voices in the first bar (the second and 
                        third voices) differ greatly with regards to their 
                        individualization. The lower voice has a distinctly 
                        structural character in comparison with the higher 
                        voice, which remains individual.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        When it enters later, the first voice begins 
                        somewhat lower than the second, seeking to leap over 
                        it, which at first it fails to do. Only after the 
                        short pause in the second voice does the first attain 
                        its coveted predominance. With the individualized 
                        entry of the first voice, the second is demoted to 
                        a structural character; due to its higher position 
                        in agreeable contrast to the third (which at this 
                        point dips slightly), the second voice makes an arc 
                        under which the first voice moves individually.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        After the yielding pause, the second voice runs 
                        parallel to the third.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        The third voice remains true to its structural 
                        character from the beginning up to the point where 
                        the second joins it in parallel; here one can detect 
                        a timid attempt at individuality.
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        A glance at the quantities of the example (insert, 
                        fig. 22) also shows that the mensural differences 
                        are based on simple and adjacent numbers. Were 
                        ratios of very small numbers to very large ones to 
                        occur in this example, then it would be a question 
                        of ornaments in music, 
                        <graphic url="..."/>
                        which, when employed all too triflingly, are called 
                        flourishes.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Syncopation.  temporal: the anticipation of the
                        force of the heavy beat value, 
                        on a light beat value.
                        positional:  overlapping of one or more 
                        boundaries between values 
                        with new values (suspended 
                        bridges)
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        January 23, 192[2]
                        Exercise: A composition of (I) individual and 
                        (II) structural rhythms. I and II are to be made 
                        organically, supporting each other reciprocally.
                    </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div_Klee_lesson5">
                <pb/> 
                    <p><graphic url=".../number5"/>January 30, 1922</p>
                    <p>
                        The time before last, I established the moment 
                        of repetition as a characteristic of structural 
                        rhythms. With a few structural examples that 
                        were fundamental due to their primitivity, we 
                        obtained, by measuring and weighing, series 
                        like:
                        1  to  1  to  1  to  1  to  1
                        or like  1+2  to  1+2  to  1+2  to  1+2
                        "   " 11+10  to  11+10  to  11+10,
                        for which we substituted the series I to I to I to I,
                        with the Roman numeral one understood as a 
                        compound unit.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        In the realm of two dimensions, in a plane, 
                        instead of these series we obtained complexes 
                        like
                        I  I  I  I
                        I  I  I  I
                        I  I  I  I
                        I  I  I  I
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        In contrast to these characters, we considered 
                        individual rhythms, taking as their basis numbers  
                        with which the moment of repetition was precluded. 
                        The prime numbers appeared to be particularly 
                        suited for this: 
                        3 to 5 to 7 to 11 to 13 to 17 to 19 to 23, etc.
                        In the following exercise, "Combination of structural
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        and individual rhythms," I warned against 
                        proceeding mathematically, because the theory 
                        is after all just an ordering of intuitively 
                        available things and plays only a retroactive 
                        role in the creative process--the role of 
                        criticism, brought to bear retroactively.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Some solutions to this exercise evinced first 
                        of all talent, and intelligence. 
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson5_fig1"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        I should mention at
                        the outset that no one
                        discovered Columbus's fish.
                        Columbus's fish
                        <graphic url="..."/>
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        In some cases, an intimate fusion of individuum and 
                        structure was sketched out, the structure obligingly 
                        following the individuum's trail, step by step.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Let us assume that fig. 1 represents the 
                        individuum. Proof: no repetition. Like an upbeat it 
                        begins at A with seventeen, plummets by a value of 
                        twenty-three, bends at a wide angle to the right with 
                        thirteen, rises vertically with three, angles left 
                        with two, drops diagonally with nineteen, angles left 
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/><graphic url="..."/>
                        <cb n="right"/>
                        with fifteen to 
                        the endpoint Z.N
                        (I ask, meanwhile, 
                        that the numbers
                        be understood not 
                        quantitatively, but 
                        qualitatively.) 
                        The result is 
                        three circumscribed 
                        planes of a non
                        repeating, and there
                        fore individual, 
                        character:
                        P5, P3
                        and P7
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        (to fig. 2)
                        With fig. 2, the structural character comes into play. 
                        The plummeting vertical divides into five, five times,* 
                        the individual thirteen in a series of threes, followed 
                        by several twos, several threes, sixes, etc.
                        *Pay attention to the points of intersection!
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        Regarding the combined figure (2), it still must be 
                        said that the measures of the individual rhythm are 
                        greater than the measures of the structure and that 
                        the individual (line-)trajectory is qualitative (or 
                        weighing), in comparison to the structure that is 
                        kept purely quantitative (measuring). *Note!
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson5_fig3"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        In this case (fig. 3) you can speak of a two-voiced 
                        trajectory, in which the individual theme is not 
                        repeatedly intersected by the structural theme, as 
                        in the previous example, but only now and then, not 
                        even in every segment.N Consequently, one cannot 
                        deny the structural theme a certain independence. It 
                        is aware of this and takes on a dynamic character 
                        in its trajectory. The individuum feels magnificent 
                        because of its higher distinctiveness, it requires 
                        no special accentuation of its ego, and it goes along 
                        separately, in quantitative stillness, flute-like, in 
                        spite of the companionship of the heavy structural
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        * I recently translated a musical construct into a 
                        pictorial construct. So now I can also think of the 
                        reverse and ask myself, how would our individuum, 
                        with its structure, sound as music? Undoubtedly as 
                        pure melody with purely accompanying subordinate 
                        forms.
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        instrumentation. The ratio of the measures in both 
                        characters corresponds to the ratios in the first 
                        example (fig. 2). The measures of the individual rhythm 
                        contain the higher numbers.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson5_fig4"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        In this new example (fig. 4), if one disregards the verticals,  
                        the structural part may be analyzed very primitively as a re- 
                        peated ratio of 1 to 1 to 1 to 1 to 1 to 1. (horizontal parallels)
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        The verticals, a bit more developed rhythmically, introduce 
                        something new, namely, alternation in pairs:
                        2a  +  2b  +  2a  +  2b 
                        (vertical alternation)
                        (1+1) (1+1)  (1+1) (1+1) (horizontal parallels)
                        Or, 
                        in sum I to I
                        In this linear representation of the structure, the manner of expression  
                        is purely mensural. If one thinks of the squares in alternating colors,*
                        The individual part of this example shows us several individuums
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        * then one must take into account the fact that different colors  
                        indicate the strongest (psychological) dynamism and that great  
                        restraint is demanded of the individuum.
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        which differ from one another without repetitions. 
                        Where they are articulated, the articulation is based 
                        on individual numbers. Their expression is dynamic 
                        (weighing) in comparison to the purely mensural 
                        manner of expression of the structural part.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Comparison of the 3 examples.
                        The first example (fig. 2) was melodic with 
                        structural accompaniment, therefore, a dominant 
                        individuum.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        The second (fig. 3) was thematic in two voices, 
                        with dynamic accentuation of the relatively structural 
                        part, therefore, a delicate individuum.
                        (delicate and devout)
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        This third example is a kind of emblem of the 
                        happy individuum or of happy individuums, which are 
                        able to arrange themselves rigorously over a wide 
                        area in conformity with the set structural pattern, 
                        without detracting from their individual character.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        For a further example I am inspired by a 
                        very lovely little collage on glass that I got to 
                        see in the last exercise (fig. 5).
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson5_fig5"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        It consisted wholly of square pieces of paper--arranged freely 
                        alongside and overlapping each other, and freely positioned 
                        horizontally/vertically and diagonally--which created a lively
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        structural rhythm. Apart from their colorfulness, they 
                        produced a dynamic particularly rich in contrast, ranging 
                        from light to very deep dark, from the way in which 
                        they overlapped, because the light was meant to shine 
                        through it from behind, as with a glass window.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        In the deep dark tonality, there was already a 
                        transition to the individual. However, the individuum 
                        received its full, most highly dynamic force of 
                        expression through the rhythmization of the squares 
                        into the complexes according to their color type: blue, 
                        red, violet, etc.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        A highly dynamic individuum arose out of colors 
                        based on a tonal-dynamic structural rhythm. (* Another possi- 
                        bility
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/>
                        (fig. 6) Finally, 
                        yet another variant, 
                        in which an accentu- 
                        ated line, borrowed 
                        from some individuum, 
                        is divided individually, 
                        and on each segment 
                        of which the struc
                        tural plane and the 
                        structureless plane 
                        face each other, 
                        in such a way that 
                        the two kinds of 
                        plane alternate, 
                        in sequences both 
                        horizontal and 
                        vertical.
                        (Lest anyone think you 
                        must work according to 
                        rules.)
                        <cb n="right"/><graphic url=".../lesson5_fig6"/>
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        Up to this point, we have moved mainly in 
                        the formal terrain of culture. In our constructing, 
                        we worked from terrestrial, human assumptions, 
                        from the way in which we are affixed to the 
                        earth, from our restricted possibilities of 
                        movement, from the limited range of physics.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        The main symbol of our activity was the pair 
                        of weighing scales, that horizontal governed by 
                        the vertical force of attraction of the ground 
                        upon which we must ever stand.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <cb n="left"/><graphic url=".../lesson5_fig7"/>
                        <cb n="right"/>
                        The simplest symbol for this force of attraction is 
                        the plumbline,  the simple vertical. The weighing 
                        scales, however, take this 
                        perpendicular into account; 
                        the perpendicular is the 
                        criterion for its position 
                        of equilibrium.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        One could thus say that the spirit of the scales is 
                        this cross:
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson5_fig8"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        Disruptions of the equilibrium of the scales produce 
                        the diagonal,
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson5_fig9"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        and their correction through a contrary disruption 
                        produces this new cross,
                        the diagonal cross.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson5_fig10"/>
                    </figure>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        Now, where does this powerful force of attraction 
                        reside?
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        In the ground: <graphic url=".../lesson5_fig11"/>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Or, if you know that this ground as a whole has 
                        the form of a ball, it resides at the center of 
                        this ball, at the center of the earth:
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson5_fig12"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        As a rule, physically, we cannot avoid this; as 
                        a rule, everything in this world must reckon 
                        with it. In particular, a construction's every 
                        stone is possessed by this force, whether they be 
                        supporting columns or the spans lying over them.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        So, as a rule, we will repeatedly occupy 
                        ourselves with problems of statics. And our own 
                        physical-human dependence on this terrestrial 
                        force facilitates our ability to draw conclusions 
                        about our fellow sufferer of this force--the 
                        construction, the physical work.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        In practice, our limited physical size and 
                        range of action compel us to start from the 
                        component, from the part of the whole.
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        That it is our lot to be thus bound should not 
                        discourage us from recognizing that above us, things 
                        can be otherwise, that there are regions where other 
                        laws hold, for which new symbols will have to be 
                        found, corresponding to movement that is looser and 
                        to places that are more mobile.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        The intermediate realm of the atmosphere, or of 
                        its heavier sibling water, may lend us a mediating 
                        hand in order to later reach the vast space of the 
                        cosmos.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        In water, as every swimmer can perceive, due to 
                        the new element and its new weight, the effect of 
                        the gravitational force determined by the earth's 
                        attraction works in the opposite direction, that is 
                        to say, upwards.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        The diver, however, can with a little effort 
                        master the entire deep space of the water like a 
                        fish--or like a bird masters the entire upper realm 
                        of the air.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson5_fig13"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>
                        He must also make partial efforts, like the mountaineer 
                        or someone climbing stairs. Nevertheless, here the 
                        fixed points of adhesion, the footprints, become 
                        unnecessary. The rhythm of swimming movements
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        above or under water is more relaxed, smoother than 
                        the rhythm of walking on the ground or climbing a 
                        mountain or stairs.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        The swimmer in the air (the pilot or the glider)  
                        must identify with his machine, and, integrated with 
                        it, he can indulge in new possibilities of movement. 
                        In a free-flying air balloon, there is altogether 
                        little to be done. One is left to forces like air 
                        currents or cooler and warmer air. The way in which 
                        air masses of differing temperature flow into one 
                        another allows for resistance-free movement.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        In outer space, finally, there are no longer 
                        any caesuras, whether rigid or smooth. Here primal 
                        movement reigns, movement as the norm.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        It is the whole that moves. The belief that we, 
                        as planet earth, are standing still and that the sun 
                        revolves around us was a delusion.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        It is a delusion to think that the sun stands 
                        still and only we, the earth, move.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Suns have orbits set in motion; the planets 
                        have orbits arranged around the orbits of the suns.
                    </p>
                    <p>It is the whole that moves.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <figDesc>
                            C center of the earth
                            W water
                            G level ground
                            M mountains
                            A atmosphere
                            F force of the earth's
                            attraction
                        </figDesc>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson5_fig14"/>
                    </figure>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        A projectile shot steeply upwards rises through 
                        the air with diminishing intensity, turns, and falls 
                        with increasing intensity back to the earth.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson5_fig15"/>
                        <figDesc>
                            First example: a (bipartite) rhythm with loose articulation, a.
                        </figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <figDesc>
                            Second ex.: a stair climber whose effort progressively 
                            increases with each step.
                        </figDesc>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson5_fig16"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <figDesc>
                            Third example: 
                            a rhythm with rigid 
                            articulation, a.
                            or alternating rigid and  
                            loose articulation.
                        </figDesc>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson5_fig17"/>
                    </figure>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                        4th example (fig. 17): A stone falls down a steep 
                        mountain slope, rebounding with leaps of increasing 
                        size. A rhythm with rigid articulation.
                    </p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson5_fig18"/>
                        <figDesc>
                            5th example: A swimmer's kicks, a rhythm with loose 
                            articulation.
                        </figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=".../lesson5_fig19"/>
                        <figDesc>
                            Sixth example (fig. 19)
                            An air balloon goes, rising from a warmer into a 
                            cooler layer of air, then again into a warmer layer 
                            and finally into a much warmer layer.
                        </figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <p>A rhythm with loose articulation.</p>
                <pb/> 
                  <figure>
                    <cb n="left"/>
                    <figDesc>
                        Seventh 
                        example.
                        A meteor 
                        describes 
                        its path, 
                        draws near 
                        the earth and 
                        through the 
                        earth's force 
                        of attraction  
                        is diverted 
                        from its course, 
                        intersects the 
                        atmosphere for 
                        a short critical 
                        moment, becomes a 
                        glowing shooting star 
                        due to the friction 
                        with the air, narrowly 
                        escapes the danger of 
                        remaining stuck forever on 
                        earth and drifts off, cooling 
                        in empty space and dying out 
                        again.
                        A cosmic form with loose articulation (a)
                    </figDesc>
                    <cb n="centre"/><graphic url=".../lesson5_fig20"/>
                    <cb n="right"/>
                    <figDesc>
                        M  meteor
                        A  atmosphere
                        E  earth
                        F  force of gravity
                        a  articulation
                    </figDesc>
                  </figure>  
                <pb/> 
                    <p>Monday, February 6, 1922</p>
                    <p>
                        Exercise: Combination of rigid and fluid (or loose) 
                        rhythms. The end result should be the composition. The 
                        tasks from earlier exercises can be incorporated.
                        E.g., applying a rigid rhythm to the individuum, a loose
                        rhythm to the structural;
                        or, applying a [loose] rhythm to the individuum, [rigid] 
                        to the structural; 
                        or, two individuums affecting each other mutually, one 
                        loose and the other rigid.
                    </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div_Klee_lesson6">
                <pb/> <!--69--> 
                <pb/> <!--70--> 
                <pb/> <!--71--> 
                <pb/> <!--72--> 
                <pb/> <!--73--> 
                <pb/> <!--74--> 
                <pb/> <!--75--> 
                <pb/> <!--76--> 
                <pb/> <!--77--> 
                <pb/> <!--78--> 
                <pb/> <!--79--> 
                <pb/> <!--80--> 
                <pb/> <!--81--> 
                <pb/> <!--82--> 
                <pb/> <!--83--> 
                <pb/> <!--84--> 
                <pb/> <!--85--> 
                <pb/> <!--86-->
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div_Klee_lesson7">
                <pb/> <!--87--> 
                <pb/> <!--88--> 
                <pb/> <!--89--> 
                <pb/> <!--90--> 
                <pb/> <!--91--> 
                <pb/> <!--92--> 
                <pb/> <!--93--> 
                <pb/> <!--94--> 
                <pb/> <!--95--> 
                <pb/> <!--96--> 
                <pb/> <!--97--> 
                <pb/> <!--98--> 
                <pb/> <!--99--> 
                <pb/> <!--100--> 
                <pb/> <!--101--> 
                <pb/> <!--102--> 
                <pb/> <!--103--> 
                <pb/> <!--104-->
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div_Klee_lesson8">
                <pb/> <!--105-->   
                <pb/> <!--106--> 
                <pb/> <!--107--> 
                <pb/> <!--108--> 
                <pb/> <!--109--> 
                <pb/> <!--110--> 
                <pb/> <!--111--> 
                <pb/> <!--112--> 
                <pb/> <!--113--> 
                <pb/> <!--114--> 
                <pb/> <!--115--> 
                <pb/> <!--116--> 
                <pb/> <!--117--> 
                <pb/> <!--118--> 
                <pb/> <!--119--> 
                <pb/> <!--120--> 
                <pb/> <!--121--> 
                <pb/> <!--122-->
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div_Klee_lesson9">
                <pb/> <!--123-->
                <pb/> <!--124-->
                <pb/> <!--125-->
                <pb/> <!--126-->
                <pb/> <!--127-->
                <pb/> <!--128-->
                <pb/> <!--129-->
                <pb/> <!--130-->
                <pb/> <!--131-->
                <pb/> <!--132-->
                <pb/> <!--133-->
                <pb/> <!--134-->
                <pb/> <!--135-->
                <pb/> <!--136-->
                <pb/> <!--137-->
                <pb/> <!--138-->
                <pb/> <!--139-->
                <pb/> <!--140-->
                <pb/> <!--141-->
                <pb/> <!--142-->
                <pb/> <!--143-->
                <pb/> <!--144-->
                <pb/> <!--145-->
                <pb/> <!--146-->
                <pb/> <!--147-->
                <pb/> <!--148-->
                <pb/> <!--149-->
                <pb/> <!--150-->
                <pb/> <!--151-->
                <pb/> <!--152-->
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div_Klee_lesson10">
                <pb/> <!--153-->
                <pb/> <!--154-->
                <pb/> <!--155-->
                <pb/> <!--156-->
                <pb/> <!--157-->
                <pb/> <!--158-->
                <pb/> <!--159-->
                <pb/> <!--160-->
                <pb/> <!--161-->
                <pb/> <!--162-->
                <pb/> <!--163-->
                <pb/> <!--164-->
                <pb/> <!--165-->
                <pb/> <!--166-->
                <pb/> <!--167-->
                <pb/> <!--168-->
                <pb/> <!--169-->
                <pb/> <!--170-->
                <pb/> <!--171-->
                <pb/> <!--172-->
            </div>
            <div xml:id="div_Klee_lesson11">
                <pb/> <!--172-->
                <pb/> <!--173-->
                <pb/> <!--174-->
                <pb/> <!--175-->
                <pb/> <!--176-->
                <pb/> <!--177-->
                <pb/> <!--178-->
                <pb/> <!--179-->
                <pb/> <!--180-->
                <pb/> <!--181-->
                <pb/> <!--182-->
                <pb/> <!--183-->
                <pb/> <!--184-->
                <pb/> <!--185-->
                <pb/> <!--186-->
                <pb/> <!--187-->
                <pb/> <!--188-->
                <pb/> <!--189-->
                <pb/> <!--190-->
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
