<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model
  href="https://vault.tei-c.org/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"
  schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
  type="application/xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
   <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Contributions to the Theory of Pictorial Form.</title>
                <author>P. Klee</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt> 
                <publisher>Istituto Italiano di Studi Germanici</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Rome</pubPlace>
                <date>2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <respStmt><resp>Translated by</resp><name></name></respStmt>
                    <respStmt><resp>Scientific responsability of</resp><name>Tiziana Mancinelli</name></respStmt>
                    <respStmt><resp>Coordinated by</resp><name>Eleonora De Longis</name></respStmt>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="div_Klee_introduction">
                <pb/>
                <head type="main">A. Winter semester lectures 1921-1922 <date>Nov. 14, 1921</date></head>
                    <p>
                       By way of introduction, a brief clarification of concepts. First, what the concept of "analysis" encompasses: In ordinary conversation one usually hears mention of chemists' analyses. For instance, a certain preparation sells well due to its excellent effect. The manufacturer's profits make other manufacturers curious, and they take a sample of it to the chemist so that he can analyze it. He must proceed methodically in order to break the preparation down into its component parts. To solve the riddle.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                       In another case, a stimulant proves to have grave consequences for health. Here also the chemist must be called upon to reveal the harmful components through an analysis.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                       In both cases the given substance is a whole composed of different, initially unknown
                   
                <pb/> 
                 
                       parts; the components are what is sought after.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                       In our business, the motives or inducements that lead us to make analyses are of course different. We do not analyze works that we would like to copy, nor works we have reason to distrust.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                       We investigate the paths that another has followed in the creation of a work in order, by becoming familiar with these paths, to get going ourselves.
                       This type of examination should prevent us from regarding the work as something rigid, immutably fixed. By means of such exercises we can prevent ourselves from sneaking up on a finished work only to quickly pluck up what stands out the most and run off with it.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                       A special type of analysis is the
                    
                <pb/> 
                
                       examination of the work through the stages of its emergence. I designate this type with the word "genesis." The first book of Moses, which deals with the creation of the world, is also called Genesis. There it is written what God created on the first day, what on the second, and so forth. The universe surrounding us undergoes a historical articulation.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                       We are makers, working practitioners, and hence it is natural that here we shall move chiefly in a formal domain, all the while not forgetting that before the formal beginning, or (put more simply) before the first stroke, lies an entire prehistory: not only, say, the yearning, the human desire to express oneself, not only the outward necessity to do so, but also a general human condition, whose orientation is called a weltanschauung, which, with an inner necessity,
                  
                <pb/> 
                  
                       urges its manifestation in this or that direction.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                       I emphasize this lest the misunderstanding arise that a work consists only of form.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                       But on the other hand, I must emphasize here even more that the most precise scientific knowledge of nature, plants, animals, the earth and its history, or of the stars is useless to us if we are not provided with all the tools for their representation; that the profoundest understanding of the synergy of these things in the universe is of no use to us if we are not also equipped with forms directed towards that purpose; that the deepest feeling, the most beautiful soul, is useless unless we have the proper forms at hand.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                       <s part="I"> Here it means renouncing the exceptional fluke that on occasion earns the dilettante honor with a successful work that</s>
                    </p>
                <pb/> 
                    <p>
                       After these general premises, I shall begin where the pictorial form actually begins, with the point that sets itself in motion.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <s part="F">can, as an isolated case, shame the professionals.</s>
                    </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
